<?xml version="1.0"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>OPERATING FORMS-2 WITH CP/M</title>
  <para>
To clarify the sequences, the CP/M prompts are included before the commands
in this Appendix.
The symbol &lt;&lt; indicates that the RETURN key or equivalent should be pressed once.
</para>
  <para>
It is assumed that CP/M is loaded, and that the issued files have been copied
to the CIS COBOL CP/M system disk.
</para>
<note>
  <para>
    FORMS-2 is preconfigured for your CRT. It can be reconfigured if
    necessary for any other special CRT.
  </para>
</note>
  <section>
    <title>FORMS-2 LOADING</title>
    <para>To load FORMS-2 as issued, the command is:</para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;FORMS2&lt;&lt;
</screen>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>FORMS 2 CHECKOUT PROGRAM COMPILATION.</title>
    <para>To compile the Check-Out program that enables you to check your fixed text and
    variable data fields, the general command is:
    </para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;COBOL basename.CHK COPYLIST&lt;&lt;
</screen>
    <para>
  In the sample runs in Chapters 2, 7 and 9, basename is, of course, DEMO1 and
DEMO2 respectively.
</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>FORMS-2 CHECK-OUT PROGRAM RUNNING</title>
    <para>The Check-Out program that enables you to check your fixed text and variable
      data fields can be loaded immediately after compilation by the general command:
    </para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;RUN basename.INT&lt;&lt;
</screen>
    <para>
  In the sample runs in Chapters 2, 7 and 9, basename is, of course, DEMO1 and
DEMO2 respectively.
</para>
    <para>To be able to load the Check-Out program directly in subsequent use the
following general command is entered:
    </para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;RUN = basename.INT&lt;&lt;
</screen>
    <para>Thereafter the general command following can be used to load the Check-Out
program:
    </para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;basename&lt;&lt;
</screen>

</section>
  <section>
    <title>FORMS-2 INDEX PROGRAM COMPILATION</title>
    <para>To enable the Index program that processes an indexed sequential data file from
your FORMS-2 screens to be compiled the following general command is entered:
</para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;COBOL basename.GEN COPYLIST&lt;&lt;
</screen>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>FORMS-2 INDEX PROGRAM RUNNING</title>
    <para>The Index program that processes an Indexed sequential data file from your
FORMS-2 screens can be loaded immediately after compilation by the general
command:
</para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;RUN basename.INT&lt;&lt;
</screen>
    <para>
In the sample run in Chapter 9 basename is, of course, DEMO2.
</para>
    <para>To be able to load the Index program directly in subsequent use the
following general command is entered:
    </para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;RUN = basename.INT&lt;&lt;
</screen>
    <para>Thereafter the general command following can be used to load the Index
program:
    </para>
    <screen>
  B&gt;basename&lt;&lt;
</screen>
  </section>
</appendix>
