<?xml version="1.0"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" version="5.0" xml:id="ciscobol" xml:lang="en" xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd">
  <info>
    <title>CIS COBOL FORMS-2 Utility Manual</title>
    <subtitle>Version 1.3</subtitle>
    <copyright>
      <year>1980, 1983</year>
      <holder>Micro Focus Ltd</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>
Not to be copied without the consent of Micro Focus.
</para>
      <para>
<address>Micro Focus Limited
<street>58 Acacia Road, St. Johns Wood</street>
<city>London</city>
<postcode>NW8 6AG</postcode>
</address>
</para>
<!--
<para><trademark class="registered">CP/M</trademark> is a trademark of Digital Research Corp. Inc.</para>
-->
</legalnotice>
    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>9</revnumber>
        <date>November 1983</date>
      </revision>
      <revision>
        <revnumber>2</revnumber>
        <date>January 1980</date>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    <publisher>
      <publishername>Micro Focus Limited</publishername>
    </publisher>
    <subjectset>
      <subject>
        <subjectterm>COBOL</subjectterm>
      </subject>
      <subject>
        <subjectterm>programming language</subjectterm>
      </subject>
      <subject>
        <subjectterm>software</subjectterm>
      </subject>
    </subjectset>
  </info>

  <preface>
    <title>WELCOME TO FORMS-2!</title>
    <para>
This manual describes your FORMS-2 package to design, create and edit
interactive screen layouts for use in CIS or L/II COBOL application programs.
</para>
<para>
  As the product is compatible with both the Micro Focus base COBOL products
CIS COBOL and LEVEL II COBOL, the common abbreviation "CIS or L/II COBOL" is
used throughout this manual.
</para>
    <para>
Most application programs will be written separately according to individual
requirements but FORMS-2 can automatically generate a powerful user-oriented
indexed data entry and filing system maintained by use of the screen layouts
(forms).
</para>
    <para>
If you want to generate an automatic indexed filing system Index program and
then use it, carry out Chapter 1 procedures, read Chapters 2 and 3 briefly
and then refer straight to Chapter 8 before performing the comprehensive
sample run in Chapter 9.</para>
    <para>
If you wish to generate some screen layouts, carry out the procedures in
Chapter 1, read briefly Chapters 2 and 3, and then perform the comprehensive
sample run in Chapter 7.
</para>
    <para>
To gain a further understanding of the FORMS-2 features and FORMS-2 operation
read Chapters 1, 2 and 3 in detail. Chapters 4, 5, 6 and 8 are descriptions
of FORMS-2 output file contents and relate directly to optional features that
can be used. Read these Chapters only if you require the feature described.
</para>
    <para>
It is recommended that, in any case, you run the sample programs before
using FORMS-2 to generate your own forms or indexed files.
</para>
    <section>
      <title>NOTATION IN THIS MANUAL</title>
      <para>
Throughout this manual, the following notation is used to describe the
format data input or output:
</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
All words printed in small letters are generic terras representing names
which will be devised by the programmer.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The carriage return (CR) or equivalent data input terminator key is
referred to throughout this manual as the RETURN key.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The symbol &lt;&lt; in this manual indicates that the RETURN key must be
pressed once.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The space bar or key is referred to throughout this manual as the
SPACE key.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>

Headings are presented in this manual in the following order of importance:
</para>
<para><literallayout>
     CHAPTER  N  
                   Chapter Heading
     TITLE
     
ORDER ONE HEADING
ORDER TWO HEADING
Order Three Heading      Text two lines down
Order Four Heading
Order Five Heading:      Text on same line
</literallayout></para>
      <para>
Numbers one (1) to nine (9) are written in text as letters, e.g. one.
</para>
      <para>
Numbers ten (10) upwards are written in text as numbers, e.g. 12.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>RELATED PUBLICATIONS</title>
      <para>
For details of CIS or L/II COBOL operation and language respectively, refer to the.
documents:
</para>
      <para><citetitle pubwork="book">CIS or Level II COBOL COBOL Operating Guide</citetitle>
                </para>
      <para><citetitle pubwork="book">CIS or Level II COBOL COBOL Language Reference Manual</citetitle>
                </para>
    </section>
    </preface>
  <xi:include href="chapter01.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter02.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter03.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter04.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter05.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter06.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter07.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter08.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="chapter09.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="appendixa.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="appendixb.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="appendixc.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="appendix-cpm.xml"/>
<!--
  <index/>
-->
  <colophon>
    <para>This book was reconstructed into DocBook format from a scanned PDF found on the Internet.
  The PDF file already had OCR performed and the text was embedded in the file.
  </para>

    <para>Source version: <?eval ${project.version}?>
  </para>
  </colophon>
</book>

